<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!--
  For editting this, see:

  http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2629.html

  In a nutshell,

  $ sudo apt-get install xml2rfc
  $ xml2rfc pubsubhubbub-core-0.1.xml pubsubhubbub-core-0.1.html

-->
<rfc category="info" docName="pubsubhubbub-core-0.1.xml" ipr="full3978">
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc private="Final" ?>

  <front>
    <title>PubSubHubbub Core 0.1 -- Working Draft</title>

    <author fullname="PubSubHubbub Team" initials="" surname="PubSubHubbub">
      <organization></organization>

      <address>
        <email>pubsubhubbub@googlegroups.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="13" month="April" year="2009" />

    <abstract>
      <t>An open, simple web-scale pubsub protocol, along with an open source
      reference implentation targetting Google App Engine. Notably, however,
      nothing in the protocol is centralized, or Google- or App
      Engine-specific. Anybody can play.</t>

      <t>As opposed to more developed (and more complex) pubsub specs like
      XEP-0060, this spec's base profile (the barrier-to-entry to speak it) is
      dead simple. The fancy bits required for high-volume publishers and
      subscribers are optional. The base profile is HTTP-based, as opposed to
      XMPP (see more on this below).</t>

      <t>To dramatically simplify the spec in several places where we had to
      choose between supporting A or B, we took it upon ourselves to say "only
      A", rather than making it an implementation decision.</t>

      <t>We offer this spec in hopes that it fills a need or at least advances
      the state of the discussion in the pubsub space. Polling sucks. We think
      a decentralized pubsub layer is a fundamental, missing layer in the
      Internet architecture today and its existence, more than just enabling
      the obvious lower latency feed readers, would enable many cool
      applications, most of which we can't even imagine. But we're looking
      forward to decentralized social networking.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Authors">
      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>Brad Fitzpatrick (brad@danga.com)</t>

          <t>Brett Slatkin (bslatkin@gmail.com)</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Notation and Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>. Domain name examples use <xref
      target="RFC2606"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definitions">
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Topic:">an Atom feed URL. The unit to which one can
          subscribe to changes. RSS isn't supported for simplicity. Further,
          the spec currently only addresses public (unauthenticated) Atom feed
          URLs.</t>

          <t hangText="Pubsub Hub (&quot;the hub&quot;):">the server (URL)
          which implements both sides of this protocol. We're currently
          implementing this and running at server at
          http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/ that's at least for now open for
          anybody to use, as either a publisher or subscriber. Any hub is free
          to implement its own policies on who can use it.</t>

          <t hangText="Publisher:">an owner of a topic. Notifies the pubsub
          hub when the topic (Atom feed) has been updated. Just notifies that
          it _has_ been updated, but not how. As in almost all pubsub systems,
          the publisher is unaware of the subscribers, if any. Other pubsub
          systems might call the publisher the "source".</t>

          <t hangText="Subscriber:">an entity (person or program) that wants
          to be notified of changed on a topic. The subscriber must be
          directly network-accessible, and is identified by Subscriber
          Callback URL.</t>

          <t hangText="Subscription:">a tuple (Topic URL, Subscriber). The
          subscription's unique key is actually the tuple (Topic URL,
          Subscriber Callback URL). ubscriptions may (at the hub's decision)
          have expiration times akin to DHCP leases and then must be
          renewed.</t>

          <t hangText="Subscriber Callback URL:">The URL at which a subscriber
          wishes to recieve notifications.</t>

          <t hangText="Event:">an event that's visible to multiple topics. For
          each event that happens (e.g. "Brad posted to the Linux
          Community."), multiple topics could be affected (e.g. "Brad posted."
          and "Linux community has new post"). Publisher events update topics,
          and the hub looks up all subscriptions for all affected topics,
          sending out notifications to subscribers.</t>

          <t hangText="Notification:">a delta on a topic, computed by the hub
          and sent to all subscribers. (TBD: format of this delta. likely: an
          Atom feed itself with just the new or changed stuff, and gravestones
          for removed items?) The notification can be the result of a
          publisher telling the hub of an update, or the hub proactively
          polling a topic feed, perhaps for a subscriber subscribing to a
          topic that's not pubsub-aware. Note also that a notification to a
          subscriber can be a payload consisting of updates for multiple
          topics. Publishers MAY choose to send multi-topic notifications as
          an optimization for heavy subscribers, but subscribers MUST
          understand them.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="High-level protocol flow">
      <t>(This section is non-normative.)</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Publishers POST a ping to their hub(s) URLs when their topic(s)
          change.</t>

          <t>Subscribers POST to one or more of the advertised hubs for a
          topic they're interested in. Alternatively, some hubs may offer
          auto-polling capability, to let {their,any} subscribers subscribe to
          topics which don't advertise a hub.</t>

          <t>The hub caches minimal metadata (id, data, entry digest) about
          each topic's previous state. When the hub refetches a topic feed (on
          its own initiative or as a result of a publisher's ping) and finds a
          delta, it enqueues a notification to all registered subscribers.
          Subscribers can be notified of topic deltas in a variety of
          ways:</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Atom Details">
      <t>Notification and source formats will be Atom. More detail follows
      this example.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[  <atom:feed>
    # ... source, title, etc ...

    <link rel="hub.subscribe" href="http://myhub.com/subscribe" />
    <link rel="self" href="http://publisher.com/happycats.xml" />
    <updated>2008-08-11T02:15:01Z</updated>

    # Example of a full entry.
    <entry>
      <title>Heathcliff</title>
      <link href="http://publisher.com/happycat25.xml" />
      <id>http://publisher.com/happycat25.xml</id>
      <updated>2008-08-11T02:15:01Z</updated>
      <content>
        What a happy cat. Full content goes here.
      </content>
    </entry>

    # Example of an entity that isn't full/is truncated. This is implied
    # by the lack of a <content> element and a <summary> element instead.
    <entry >
      <title>Heathcliff</title>
      <link href="http://publisher.com/happycat25.xml" />
      <id>http://publisher.com/happycat25.xml</id>
      <updated>2008-08-11T02:15:01Z</updated>
      <summary>
        What a happy cat!
      </summary>
    </entry>
    
    # Meta-data only; implied by the lack of <content> and <summary> elements.
    <entry>
      <title>Garfield</title>
      <link rel="alternate" href="http://publisher.com/happycat24.xml" />
      <id>http://publisher.com/happycat25.xml</id>
      <updated>2008-08-11T02:15:01Z</updated>
    </entry>

    # Context entry that's meta-data only and not new. Implied because the
    # update time on this entry is before the //atom:feed/updated time.
    <entry>
      <title>Nermal</title>
      <link rel="alternate" href="http://publisher.com/happycat23s.xml" />
      <id>http://publisher.com/happycat25.xml</id>
      <updated>2008-07-10T12:28:13Z</updated>
    </entry>

  </atom:feed>
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Publisher makes the decision as to include full body, truncated body,
      or meta data of most recent event(s). One of:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>URL + metadata</t>

          <t>URL + metadata + truncated</t>

          <t>URL + metadata + full</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The trade-off between including all content in outgoing notifications
      or having the thundering herd (by clients who fetch the
      //atom:feed/entry/link in response to a notification) is up to the
      publisher.</t>

      <t>Entries of most recent 10 events (for recipient to know whether or
      not they'd missed any recent items... like TCP SACK) will be provided as
      context. This is implied by the difference between the
      //atom:feed/updated field and the //atom:feed/entry/updated fields. The
      //atom:feed/updated field will be set to the time of the *oldest*
      &lt;entry&gt; in the list that is new. All &lt;entry&gt; items with
      &lt;updated&gt; times before then are context; all with times equal to
      or after are new. This also lets subscribers know how long it has been
      from when the notification was first sent by the publisher to when they
      actually received it from the hub.</t>

      <t>The //atom:feed/link[@rel="self"] element will indicate the original
      URL for the entire event stream with no truncation (if available).</t>

      <t>The //atom:feed/link[@rel="hub.delegate"] element indicates the URL
      that the hub should use for retrieving new notifications from a
      publisher. The publisher can make this delegate URL contain a meta-data
      only or truncated view of the feed. If a hub.delegate is not provided,
      then the 'self' URL is used as both the source of notifications and the
      source for the topic URL feed.</t>

      <t>Topic URLs must be unique, but multiple topics may use the same
      hub.delegate. In this situation, the delegate URL may serve a
      &lt;OLD_INFO&gt;MIME multipart response, each part of which will contain
      a separate Atom document for an individual topic&lt;/OLD_INFO&gt;. The
      hub must understand this delegation. Once it has fetched the topic URL
      once to see this delegation is present, it will use the delegation url
      to pull the feed. This allows the publisher to be more efficient at
      publishing across many topics at once with a single fetch from the
      hub.</t>

      <t>TODO: How do you indicate to the hub that you no longer want to have
      a delegate URL?</t>

      <t>Requirement is that topic URLs and delegate URLs can never
      overlap!</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Subscribing">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Subscriber Sends Subscription Request">
        <t>Subscription is initiated by the subscriber making a POST request
        to the Hub URL. This request has a Content-type of <spanx
        style="verb">application/x-www-form-urlencoded</spanx> and the
        following parameters in its body:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="hub.mode">REQUIRED. The literal string
            "subscribe"</t>

            <t hangText="hub.callback">REQUIRED. The subscriber's callback
            URL.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.topic">REQUIRED. The topic URL that the
            subscriber wishes to subscribe to.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.verify">REQUIRED. Comma-separated list of
            keywords describing verification modes supported by this
            subscriber, as described below.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.verify_token">A subscriber-provided opaque token
            that will be echoed back in the verification request to assist the
            subscriber in identifying which subscription request is being
            verified. If this is not included, no token will be included in
            the verification request.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The following keywords are supported for hub.verify:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="sync">The subscriber supports synchronous
            verification, where the verification request must occur before the
            subscription request returns.</t>

            <t hangText="async">The subscriber supports asynchronous
            verification, where the verification request may occur at a later
            point after the subscription request has returned.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Where multiple keywords are used, their order indicates the
        subscriber's order of preference. Hubs MUST ignore verify mode
        keywords that they do not understand. Subscribers MUST use at least
        one of the modes indicated in the list above, but MAY include
        additional keywords defined by extension specifications.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Publishing">
      <t></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2606">
        <front>
          <title>Reserved Top Level DNS Names</title>

          <author fullname="D. Eastlake" initials="D.E" surname="Eastlake">
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Panitz" initials="A.P" surname="Panitz">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2606" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement
          Levels</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="B.S" surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Alis Technologies</organization>
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2616">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1</title>

          <author fullname="R. Fielding" initials="R.F" surname="Fielding">
            <organization>UC Irvine</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Gettys" initials="J.G" surname="Gettys">
            <organization>Compaq/W3C</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Mogul" initials="J.M" surname="Mogul">
            <organization>Compaq</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="H. Frystyk" initials="H.F" surname="Frystyk">
            <organization>W3C/MIT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="L. Masinter" initials="L.M" surname="Masinter">
            <organization>Xerox</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="P. Leach" initials="P.L" surname="Leach">
            <organization>Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Berners-Lee" initials="T.L"
                  surname="Berners-Lee">
            <organization>W3C/MIT</organization>
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2616" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2617">
        <front>
          <title>HTTP Authentication: Basic and Digest Access
          Authentication</title>

          <author fullname="J. Franks" initials="J.F" surname="Franks">
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author fullname="P. Hallam-Baker" initials="P.HB"
                  surname="Hallam-Baker">
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Hostetler" initials="J.H" surname="Hostetler">
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Lawrence" initials="S.L" surname="Lawrence">
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author fullname="P. Leach" initials="P.L" surname="Leach">
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Luotonen" initials="A.L" surname="Luotonen">
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author fullname="L. Stewart" initials="L.S" surname="Stewart">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2617" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3629">
        <front>
          <title>UTF-8, a transformation format of Unicode and ISO
          10646</title>

          <author fullname="Francois Yergeau" initials="F.Y" surname="Yergeau">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3629" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3986">
        <front>
          <title>Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax</title>

          <author fullname="T. Berners-Lee" initials="T.L"
                  surname="Berners-Lee">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3986" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2045">
        <front>
          <title>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part One: Format
          of Internet Message Bodies</title>

          <author fullname="N. Freed" initials="N.F" surname="Freed">
            <organization>Innosoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="N. Borenstein" initials="N.B" surname="Borenstein">
            <organization>First Virtual</organization>
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2045" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
