<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!--
  For editting this, see:

  http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2629.html

  In a nutshell,

  $ sudo apt-get install xml2rfc
  $ xml2rfc pubsubhubbub-core-0.1.xml pubsubhubbub-core-0.1.html

-->
<rfc category="info" docName="pubsubhubbub-core-0.4.xml" ipr="full3978">
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc strict="no" ?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc private="Draft" ?>

  <front>
    <title>PubSubHubbub Core 0.4 -- Working Draft</title>

    <author fullname="Brad Fitzpatrick" initials="B." surname="Fitzpatrick">
      <organization>Google, Inc</organization>

      <address>
        <email>brad@danga.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Brett Slatkin" initials="B." surname="Slatkin">
      <organization>Google, Inc</organization>

      <address>
        <email>bslatkin@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Martin Atkins" initials="M." surname="Atkins">
      <organization>Six Apart Ltd.</organization>

      <address>
        <email>mart@degeneration.co.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Julien Genestoux" initials="M." surname="Genestoux">
      <organization>Notifixious Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <email>julien@superfeedr.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="5" month="February" year="2012" />

    <abstract>
      <t>An open, simple, web-scale and decentralized pubsub protocol. 
          Anybody can play.</t>

      <t>As opposed to more developed (and more complex) pubsub specs like <xref
      target="XEP-0060">Jabber Publish-Subscribe</xref> this spec's base profile
      (the barrier-to-entry to speak it) is dead simple. The fancy bits required
      for high-volume publishers and subscribers are optional. The base profile
      is HTTP-based, as opposed to XMPP (see more on this below).</t>

      <t>To dramatically simplify this spec in several places where we had to
      choose between supporting A or B, we took it upon ourselves to say "only
      A", rather than making it an implementation decision.</t>

      <t>We offer this spec in hopes that it fills a need or at least advances
      the state of the discussion in the pubsub space. Polling sucks. We think
      a decentralized pubsub layer is a fundamental, missing layer in the
      Internet architecture today and its existence, more than just enabling
      the obvious lower latency feed readers, would enable many cool
      applications, most of which we can't even imagine. But we're looking
      forward to decentralized social networking.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Notation and Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>. Domain name examples use <xref
      target="RFC2606"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definitions">
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Topic:">An HTTP resource URL. The
          unit to which one can subscribe to changes. </t>

          <t hangText="Hub (&quot;the hub&quot;):">The server (<xref
          target="RFC3986">URL</xref>) which implements both sides of this
          protocol. Any hub MAY implement its own policies on who can use it.</t>

          <t hangText="Publisher:">An owner of a topic. Notifies the hub when
          the topic feed has been updated. As in almost all pubsub systems, the 
          publisher is unaware of the subscribers, if any. Other pubsub systems 
          might call the publisher the "source".</t>

          <t hangText="Subscriber:">An entity (person or program) that wants
          to be notified of changes on a topic. The subscriber must be
          directly network-accessible and is identified by its Subscriber
          Callback URL.</t>

          <t hangText="Subscription:">A unique relation to a topic by a
          subscriber that indicates it should receive updates for that topic. A
          subscription's unique key is the tuple (Topic URL, Subscriber Callback
          URL). Subscriptions may (at the hub's decision) have expiration times
          akin to DHCP leases which must be periodically renewed.</t>

          <t hangText="Subscriber Callback URL:">The <xref
          target="RFC3986">URL</xref> at which a subscriber wishes to receive
          notifications.</t>

          <t hangText="Event:">An event that causes updates to multiple topics.
          For each event that happens (e.g. "Brad posted to the Linux
          Community."), multiple topics could be affected (e.g. "Brad posted."
          and "Linux community has new post"). Publisher events cause topics to
          be updated and the hub looks up all subscriptions for affected topics,
          sending out notifications to subscribers.</t>

          <t hangText="Notification:">A payload describing how a topic's
          contents have changed, or the full cupdated content. 
          Depending on the topic's content type, the difference (or "delta") may be 
          computed by the hub and sent to all subscribers.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="High-level protocol flow">
      <t>(This section is non-normative.)</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Publishers notify their hub(s) URLs when their topic(s)
          change.</t>

          <t>Subscribers POST to one or more of the advertised hubs for a
          topic they're interested in. Alternatively, some hubs may offer
          auto-polling capability, to let {their,any} subscribers subscribe to
          topics which don't advertise a hub.</t>

          <t>The hub caches minimal metadata (id, data, entry digest) about
          each topic's previous state. When the hub re-fetches a topic feed (on
          its own initiative or as a result of a publisher's ping) and finds a
          delta, it enqueues a notification to all registered subscribers.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="discovery" title="Discovery">
      <t>A potential subscriber initiates discovery by retrieving the topic to
      which it wants to subscribe. The HTTP response from the publisher MUST
      include at least one <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Url</spanx> 
      HTTP header, as well as exactly one <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Self-Url</spanx> 
      HTTP header. The <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Url</spanx> MUST 
      indicate the exact url of the PubSubHubbub hub designated by the publisher.
      If more than one url is specified, it is expected that the publisher pings each
      of these urls, so the subscriber may subscribe to one or more of these.
      The <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Self-Url</spanx> will point to the
      permanent URL for the resource being polled.</t>

      <t>Example:</t>

    <t>Hubs should provide an <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref> interface and publishers 
    SHOULD use <xref target="RFC2616">HTTPS</xref> in their hubs' discovery URLs. 
    However, subscribers that do not support <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref> MAY
    try to fallback to <xref target="RFC2616">HTTP</xref>, which MAY work
    depending on the hub's policy. If the advertised url is <xref target="RFC2616">HTTP</xref>, 
    subscriber MAY choose to try <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref> first.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="subscribing" title="Subscribing and Unsubscribing">
      <t>Subscribing to a topic URL consists of four parts that may occur
      immediately in sequence or have a delay.</t>
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Requesting a subscription using the hub</t>
          <t>Confirming the subscription was actually desired</t>
          <t>Receiving an acknowledgement from the hub that the subscription was accepted (OPTIONAL).</t>
          <t>Periodically reconfirming the subscription is still active</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Unsubscribing works in the same way, except with a single parameter
      changed to indicate the desire to unsubscribe.</t>

      <section title="Subscriber Sends Subscription Request">
        <t>Subscription is initiated by the subscriber making an <xref target="RFC2616">HTTPS</xref>
        or <xref target="RFC2616">HTTP</xref> POST request to the hub URL. This request
        has a Content-Type of <spanx
        style="verb">application/x-www-form-urlencoded</spanx> (described in
        Section 17.13.4 of <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/>) and the
        following parameters in its body:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="hub.callback">REQUIRED. The subscriber's callback URL 
            where notifications should be delivered. The subscriber's
            callback URL SHOULD be unique for each subscription.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.mode">REQUIRED. The literal string "subscribe" or
            "unsubscribe", depending on the goal of the request.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.topic">REQUIRED. The topic URL that the subscriber
            wishes to subscribe to.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.lease_seconds">OPTIONAL. Number of seconds for
            which the subscriber would like to have the subscription active. If
            not present or an empty value, the subscription will be permanent
            (or active until <xref target="autorefresh">automatic
            refreshing</xref> removes the subscription). Hubs MAY choose to
            respect this value or not, depending on their own policies. This
            parameter MAY be present for unsubscription requests and MUST be
            ignored by the hub in that case.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.secret">OPTIONAL. A subscriber-provided secret
            string that will be used to compute an HMAC digest for <xref
            target="authednotify">authorized content distribution</xref>. If not
            supplied, the HMAC digest will not be present for content
            distribution requests. This parameter SHOULD only be specified when
            the request was made over <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref>. This
            parameter MUST be less than 200 bytes in length.</t>

          </list></t>

          <t>Hubs MUST ignore additional request parameters they do not
          understand.</t>

          <t>Hubs MUST allow subscribers to re-request subscriptions that are
          already activate. Each subsequent request to a hub to subscribe or
          unsubscribe MUST override the previous subscription state for a
          specific topic URL and callback URL combination once the action is
          verified. Any failures to confirm the subscription action MUST leave
          the subscription state unchanged. This is required so subscribers can
          renew their subscriptions before the lease seconds period is over
          without any interruption.</t>

        <section title="Subscription Parameter Details">

          <t>The topic and callback URLs MAY use <xref target="RFC2616">HTTP</xref> 
          or <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref> schemes. The topic URL MUST 
          be the one advertised by the publisher in the <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Self-Url</spanx> 
          Header during the discovery phase. (See <xref target="discovery"></xref>).
          Hubs MAY refuse subscriptions if the topic url does not correspond to the one
          advertised by the publisher. The topic URL can otherwise be free-form 
          following <xref target="RFC3986">the URI spec</xref>. Hubs MUST always 
          decode non-reserved characters for these URL parameters; see section 2.4 on 
          <spanx style="emph">"When to Encode or Decode"</spanx> in <xref
          target="RFC3986">the URI spec</xref>.</t>

          <t>The callback URL MAY contain arbitrary query string parameters
          (e.g., <spanx style="verb">?foo=bar&red=fish</spanx>). Hubs MUST
          preserve the query string during subscription verification by
          appending new parameters to the end of the list using the <spanx
          style="verb">&</spanx> (ampersand) character to join. Existing
          parameters with names that overlap with those used by verification
          requests will not be overwritten; Hubs MUST only append verification
          parameters to the existing list, if any. For event notification, the
          callback URL will be POSTed to including any query-string parameters
          in the URL portion of the request, not as POST body parameters.</t>

          <t>Subscribers MAY choose to use <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref>
          for their callback URLs if they care about the privacy of
          notifications as they come over the wire from the Hub (see <xref target="authednotify"></xref>)</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Subscription Response Details">
          
          <t>The hub MUST respond to a subscription request with an HTTP 202 "Accepted" 
          response to indicate that the request was received and will now 
          be verified (<xref target="verifysub"></xref>) and validated (<xref 
          target="validationsub"></xref>) by the hub. The hub SHOULD perform the 
          verification of intent as soon as possible.</t>
          
           <t>If a hub finds any errors in the subscription request, an
          appropriate HTTP error response code (4xx or 5xx) MUST be returned. In
          the event of an error, hubs SHOULD return a description of the error
          in the response body as plain text. Hubs MAY decide to reject some
          callback URLs or topic URLs based on their own policies (e.g., domain
          authorization, topic URL port numbers).</t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="verifysub" title="Hub Verifies Intent of the Subscriber">
        <t>In order to prevent an attacker from creating unwanted subscriptions
        on behalf of a subscriber (or unsubscribing desired ones), a hub must
        ensure that the subscriber did indeed send the subscription request.</t>

        <t>The hub verifies a subscription request by sending an <xref
        target="RFC2616">HTTP</xref> GET request to the subscriber's callback
        URL as given in the subscription request. This request has the following
        query string arguments appended (format described in Section 17.13.4 of
        <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/>):</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="hub.mode">REQUIRED. The literal string "subscribe" or
            "unsubscribe", which matches the original request to the hub from
            the subscriber.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.topic">REQUIRED. The topic URL given in the
            corresponding subscription request.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.challenge">REQUIRED. A hub-generated, random string
            that MUST be echoed by the subscriber to verify the
            subscription.</t>

            <t hangText="hub.lease_seconds">REQUIRED/OPTIONAL. The
            hub-determined number of seconds that the subscription will stay
            active before expiring, measured from the time the verification
            request was made from the hub to the subscriber. Hubs MUST supply
            this parameter for subscription requests. This parameter MAY be
            present for unsubscribe requests and MUST be ignored by subscribers
            during unsubscription.</t>

          </list></t>

        <section title="Verification Details">

          <t>The subscriber MUST confirm that the <spanx style="verb">hub.topic
          </spanx> correspond to a pending subscription or unsubscription that it 
          wishes to carry out. If so, the subscriber MUST respond with an HTTP 
          success (2xx) code with a response body equal to the <spanx
          style="verb">hub.challenge</spanx> parameter. If the subscriber does
          not agree with the action, the subscriber MUST respond with a 404 "Not
          Found" response.</t>

          <t>The hub MUST consider other server response codes (3xx, 4xx, 5xx) 
          to mean that the verification request has failed. If the subscriber
          returns an HTTP success (2xx) but the content body does not match the
          <spanx style="verb">hub.challenge</spanx> parameter, the hub MUST also
          consider verification to have failed.</t>
          
          <t>Hubs MAY make the <spanx style="verb">hub.lease_seconds</spanx>
          equal to the period the subscriber passed in their subscription
          request but MAY change the value depending on the hub's policies. To
          sustain a temporary subscription, the subscriber MUST re-request the
          subscription on the hub before <spanx
          style="verb">hub.lease_seconds</spanx> seconds has elapsed. For
          permanent subscriptions with no <spanx
          style="verb">hub.lease_seconds</spanx> value specified, the behavior
          is different as described in the section on <xref
          target="autorefresh">automatic subscription refreshing</xref>.</t>

        </section>
        
        <section title="Subscription Validation" anchor="validationsub">
          <t>Subscriptions MAY be validated by the Hubs who may require 
          more details to accept or refuse a subscription. The Hub MAY also
          check with the publisher whether the subscription should be accepted.</t>
          
          <t>If (and when), the subscription has been accepted,
          the hub MUST indicate it to the subscriber by performing a notification
          of the current state of the resource to the subscriber (see <xref target="contentdistribution" />). 
          (this is optional in synchronous mode). The subscriber will use this has 
          an indication that its subscription has been confirmed.</t>
          
          <t>Additionally, this notification MUST include a <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Self-Url</spanx>
          HTTP header which indicates to the subscriber to what feed he has been subscribed.
          This feed url MAY be different from the feed for which the subscriber has initially subscribed,
          as the publisher MAY have considered that this one was better suited for the subscriber.
          (This is specifically useful in the context of private content with limited distribution.)</t>

          <t>If (and when), the subscription is denied, the hub will inform the subscriber
          by sending an <xref target="RFC2616">HTTP</xref> GET request to the subscriber's 
          callback URL as given in the subscription request. This request has the following
          query string arguments appended (format described in Section 17.13.4 of 
          <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224"/>):</t>
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="hub.mode">REQUIRED. The literal string "denied".</t>
            <t hangText="hub.topic">REQUIRED. The topic URL given in the corresponding 
            subscription request.</t>
            <t hangText="hub.reason">OPTIONAL. The hub may include a reason
            for which the subscription has been denied.</t>
          </list></t>
          
          <t>The subscription may be intentionally denied by the hub at any point (even
          if it was previously accepted). The Subscriber SHOULD then consider that
          the subscription is not possible anymore.</t>
              
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="autorefresh" title="Automatic Subscription Refreshing">

        <t>Before a subscription expires (i.e., before <spanx
        style="verb">hub.lease_seconds</spanx> elapses), Hubs MUST recheck with
        subscribers to see if a continued subscription is desired. Hubs do this
        by sending the subscriber a <xref target="verifysub">verification
        request</xref> with <spanx style="verb">hub.mode</spanx> equal to
        subscribe. This request MUST match the original verification request
        sent to the subscriber (but with a new <spanx style="verb">hub.challenge
        </spanx>).</t>

        <t>The response codes returned by the subscriber MUST be interpreted the
        same way as during a subscriber-initiated verification flow. However,
        this refresh request MUST behave like an initial subscription request;
        this means that if an auto-refresh response from the subscriber
        constantly returns an error, the hub MUST give up on the subscription
        verification action altogether and remove the subscription.</t>

        <t>In the case of permanent subscriptions (with no <spanx
        style="verb">hub.lease_seconds</spanx> specified in the original
        request), the <spanx style="verb">hub.lease_seconds</spanx> value
        supplied by the hub in the verification request to the subscriber SHOULD
        represent how many seconds until the hub expects it will next initiate
        automatic subscription refreshing to ensure that the subscriber is still
        interested in the topic. This behavior provides the best of both worlds:
        maximum simplicity of the subscriber through infinitely-long
        subscriptions, but still garbage collectable subscriptions for hub
        hygiene.</t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="publishing" title="Publishing">
      <t>The publisher MUST inform the hub it previously designated when a topic 
      has been updated. The hub and the publisher CAN agree on any mechanism, as 
      long as the hub is eventually able send the updated payload to the 
      subscribers.</t>
    </section>

      <section anchor="contentdistribution" title="Content Distribution">

        <t>A content distribution request is an <xref
        target="RFC2616">HTTP</xref> POST request from hub to the subscriber's
        callback URL with the payload of the notification. This request MUST
        have a <spanx style="verb">Content-Type</spanx> corresponding to the 
        type of the topic. The hub MAY reduce the payload to a diff if its format
        allows it.</t>
        
        <t>The POST request must include a <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Self-Url</spanx> 
        and a <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Url</spanx> HTTP headers that correspond
        to topic's url, as well as hub.</t>

        <t>The successful response from the subscriber's callback URL MUST be an
        HTTP success (2xx) code. The hub MUST consider all other subscriber
        response codes as failures; that means subscribers MUST not use HTTP
        redirects for moving subscriptions. The response body from the
        subscriber MUST be ignored by the hub. Hubs SHOULD retry notifications
        repeatedly until successful (up to some reasonable maximum over a
        reasonable time period). Subscribers SHOULD respond to notifications as
        quickly as possible; their success response code SHOULD only indicate
        receipt of the message, not acknowledgment that it was successfully
        processed by the subscriber.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="authednotify" title="Authenticated Content Distribution">

        <t>If the subscriber supplied a value for <spanx
        style="verb">hub.secret</spanx> in their subscription request, the hub
        MUST generate an HMAC signature of the payload and include that
        signature in the request headers of the content distribution request.
        The <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Signature</spanx> header's value MUST be
        in the form <spanx style="verb">sha1=signature</spanx> where <spanx
        style="verb">signature</spanx> is a 40-byte, hexadecimal representation
        of a <xref target="RFC3174">SHA1 signature</xref>. The signature MUST be
        computed using the <xref target="RFC2104">HMAC algorithm</xref> with the
        request body as the data and the <spanx style="verb">hub.secret</spanx>
        as the key.</t>

        <t>When subscribers receive a content distribution request with the
        <spanx style="verb">X-Hub-Signature</spanx> header specified, they
        SHOULD recompute the SHA1 signature with the shared secret using the
        same method as the hub. If the signature does not match, subscribers
        MUST still return a 2xx success response to acknowledge receipt, but
        locally ignore the message as invalid. Using this technique along with
        <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref> for subscription requests enables 
        simple subscribers to receive authenticated content delivery from hubs 
        without the need for subscribers to run an HTTPS server.</t>
        
        <t>Please note however that this signature only ensures that the payload
        was not forged. Since the notification also includes headers, these should
        not be considered as safe by the subscriber, unless of course the subscriber
        uses <xref target="RFC2818">HTTPS</xref> callbacks.</t>

      </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="References">

      <reference anchor='RFC2104'>
        <front>
          <title abbrev='HMAC'>HMAC: Keyed-Hashing for Message Authentication</title>
          <author initials='H.' surname='Krawczyk' fullname='Hugo Krawczyk'>
            <organization>IBM, T.J. Watson Research Center</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='M.' surname='Bellare' fullname='Mihir Bellare'>
            <organization>University of California at San Diego, Dept of Computer Science and Engineering</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Canetti' fullname='Ran Canetti'>
            <organization>IBM T.J. Watson Research Center</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2104' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2606">
        <front>
          <title>Reserved Top Level DNS Names</title>

          <author fullname="D. Eastlake" initials="D.E" surname="Eastlake">
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Panitz" initials="A.P" surname="Panitz">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2606" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement
          Levels</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="B.S" surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Alis Technologies</organization>
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2616">
        <front>
          <title>Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1</title>

          <author fullname="R. Fielding" initials="R.F" surname="Fielding">
            <organization>UC Irvine</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Gettys" initials="J.G" surname="Gettys">
            <organization>Compaq/W3C</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Mogul" initials="J.M" surname="Mogul">
            <organization>Compaq</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="H. Frystyk" initials="H.F" surname="Frystyk">
            <organization>W3C/MIT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="L. Masinter" initials="L.M" surname="Masinter">
            <organization>Xerox</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="P. Leach" initials="P.L" surname="Leach">
            <organization>Microsoft</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Berners-Lee" initials="T.L"
                  surname="Berners-Lee">
            <organization>W3C/MIT</organization>
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2616" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC2818'>
        <front>
        <title>HTTP Over TLS</title>
        <author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'>
        <organization /></author>
        <date year='2000' month='May' />
        <abstract>
        <t>This memo describes how to use Transport Layer Security (TLS) to secure Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) connections over the Internet.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2818' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='15170' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2818.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3174'>
        <front>
        <title>US Secure Hash Algorithm 1 (SHA1)</title>
        <author initials='D.' surname='Eastlake' fullname='D. Eastlake'>
        <organization /></author>
        <author initials='P.' surname='Jones' fullname='P. Jones'>
        <organization /></author>
        <date year='2001' month='September' />
        <abstract>
        <t>The purpose of this document is to make the SHA-1 (Secure Hash Algorithm 1) hash algorithm conveniently available to the Internet community.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3174' />

        <format type='TXT' octets='35525' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3174.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3986">
        <front>
          <title>Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax</title>

          <author fullname="T. Berners-Lee" initials="T.L"
                  surname="Berners-Lee">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3986" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='W3C.REC-html401-19991224'
                 target='http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-html401-19991224'>
        <front>
          <title>HTML 4.01 Specification</title>

          <author initials='D.' surname='Raggett' fullname='David Raggett'>
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author initials='A.' surname='Hors' fullname='Arnaud Le Hors'>
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author initials='I.' surname='Jacobs' fullname='Ian Jacobs'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month='December' day='24' year='1999' />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name='World Wide Web Consortium Recommendation' value='REC-html401-19991224' />
        <format type='HTML' target='http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-html401-19991224' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="XEP-0060">
        <front>
          <title>Publish-Subscribe</title>
          <author initials="P." surname="Millard" fullname="Peter Millard">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Meijer" fullname="Ralph Meijer">
            <organization/>
          </author>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="XSF XEP" value="0060"/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0060.html"/>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section title="Specification Feedback">
      <t>Feedback on this specification is welcomed via the
      pubsubhubbub mailing list, pubsubhubbub@googlegroups.com.  For
      more information, see <eref
      target="http://groups.google.com/group/pubsubhubbub">the
      PubSubHubbub group on Google Groups</eref>.  Also, check out the
      <eref
      target="http://moderator.appspot.com/#15/e=43e1a&t=426ac">FAQ</eref>
      and <eref target="http://code.google.com/p/pubsubhubbub/">other
      documentation</eref>.
      </t>

     </section>
   </back>
</rfc>
